# 我的朝牌（面食）做多少卖多少
My "Chao Pai" (dough food) sell as quick as I make them.
# 早上5点钟起床 到下午6点钟一直在做
I wake up at 5 in the morning and make dough food until 6 pm.
# 超过6点再来买的 也不做了
The shop is closed after 6.
# 俺爷爷打朝牌 俺老爹打朝牌
My grand father and my father are both in this business.
# 我是第三辈打朝牌
I'm the third generation.
# （顾客）独一份 这刘家朝牌
(Customer) This "Liu Jia Chao Pai" is incomparable.
# 哈喽 今天天气特别好
Hello. It's a nice day today.
# 雪鱼将要去一个小镇上
Xueyu is going to a small town.
# 吃一个特别有名的朝牌
To taste a very famous "Chao Pai".
# 朝牌1块钱一个
One for 1￥.
# 刚出炉的时候 面香特别勾人
The nice smell of flour when they are taken out of the stove is enticing.
# 我已经好久没有吃了
I haven't eaten any for a long time.
# 想想都觉得过瘾 走吧
Just thinking of it makes me satisfied. Let's go.
# 好像上一炉烤牌刚被卖完
Looks like the last batch was just sold out.
# 阿姨  还得等多长时间
Auntie, how long do I have to wait?
# 10分钟
10 minutes.
# 好久没有等刚出炉的朝牌了
It has been a long time since I last wait for freshly made "Chao Pai".
# 这还是开年头一次
This is the first time in a new year.
# 之前来的时候还是1块钱一个
Before it was one for 1￥.
# 这次来发现 （价格）涨了5毛钱
Now (the price) goes up by 50 cents.
# 不过1块钱的价格 确实卖了很多年了
But the 1￥ price has been around for quite some years.
# 看牌子 价格也是刚涨没有多久
The price increase was made not long ago, judging by this new sign.
# 已经是30年老店
This is a 30-year-old brand.
# 阿姨擀好朝牌 会在上面刷油
After rolling the dough, auntie will brush some oil on top.
# 然后撒上芝麻盐
And sprinkle some sesame salt.
# 这样吃起来就不会像馒头那样
So it doesn't taste, like steam bread,
# 没有什么样的味道
that bland.
# 在阿姨做朝牌的时候 你会发现
You can see when making "Chao Pai",
# 芝麻放的特别多
auntie put a lot of sesame.
# 感觉这一整面都是芝麻
This side is all sesame.
# 你再多放一粒 芝麻都会掉下来
Feels like if you put one more it will fall off.
# 阿姨 这一炉一次能做出来多少个 我想买10个
Auntie, how many in a batch? I want 10.
# 一炉24个
24 in one stove.
# 能放几天
How long can I store it?
# 一个星期左右
About a week.
# 它越搁越软 面和其它家不同
It turns soft over time. The flour is special.
# 1.5元一个
one for 1.5￥.
# 敞开袋子的口
Leave the plastic bag loose.
# （顾客）我不想要热的
(Customer) I don't want hot ones.
# 我要带走的 怕热的哈气 就不好了
I need to take it away. Hot steam makes it less appealing.
# 在马头镇这边 朝牌是非常出名的
Here at "Ma Tou Zhen" (literally Horse Head Town), "Chao Pai" is very well-known.
# 它为什么叫朝牌呢
Why is it called "Chao Pai" (literally "Meeting Board")?
# 是因为每一个朝牌的样子
Because every one of them,
# 很像古代 朝见君王拿的玉牌
looks like the jade board a courtier holds when meeting the emperor in ancient China.
# 像不像
Doesn't it?
# 它这个是刚打出来的
This is freshly made.
# 上面铺了密密麻麻的白芝麻
Covered with white sesame.
# 看起来就是特别酥脆 特别香
It looks crispy and smells good.
# 现在我就趁热掰一下朝牌
Now I'll split it in half.
# 听到这个声音 你都会觉得它特别美味
You can imagine how delicious it is by the sound.
# 看呀
Look.
# 里面是刷了油 加了盐的
There's oil and salt inside.
# 所以 即使是这么吃
So even though you are eating it dry,
# 你也会觉得它很有味道
you will find it flavorful.
# 一口下去
A mouthful bite,
# 满满的都是芝麻的香味
brings full of the nice sesame smell.
# 这一个朝牌分量还是很大的
One "Chao Pai" is quite big.
# 吃一个就差不多能够饱了
You may feel full after eating one.
# 平常呢 可以当主食来吃
Usually, it is a staple food.
# 你看很多做羊肉汤的地方
You can see many Lamp Soup restaurants,
# （汤）都会配朝牌来吃
serving "Chao Pai" (with soup).
# 它也可以叫烤牌 因为是烤出来的
It is also called "Kao Pai" (literally Baked Board), because it's baked dough.
# 另一方面呢 如果说平常饿了
On the other hand, if you feel hungry,
# 用它来当一下点心 也是很不错的
it can also be served as a nice pastry.
# 补充一下 在做羊肉汤的地方
As a side note, at those Lamp Soup places,
# 配的朝牌 烤牌可不是这个重量的
"Chao Pai" has a different size.
# 一般的话 会比较薄一些
Normally, it's thinner.
# 如果换成这样大的 普通人的饭量
If switching to those bigger ones, for a regular person's stomach,
# 吃一两个也就饱了
one or two is enough.
# 真的没有想到 这么简单的1块钱的小吃
It's beyond imagination this simple 1￥ pastry
# 能在这个小镇上红火几十年
at this small town can be so popular for several decades.
# 我刚买完朝牌
Right after I bought "Chao Pai",
# 后面已经有人在等着下一炉了
there were already people waiting for the next batch.
# 你知道吗 在我的朋友圈有很多
You know, I have many friends who
# 做熟食的朋友
make hot deli food.
# 他们做的肉食 熟食真的会让我垂涎三尺
Their cooked meat really makes me hungry.
# 感觉把我的馋虫都给勾出来了
Enticing all my taste buds.
# 今天呢 趁着开车出去
Today, since we are driving a car,
# 我们去买一个当地比较特色的熟食 肉食
we will buy a special local deli food -
# 就是烧鸡
braised chicken.
# 小的时候 都是逢年过节才能够吃得到
When I was little, I can only eat braised chicken during festivals and holidays.
# 待会就开个远路
Later we will take a detour,
# 去尝一尝小时候的味道
and taste the flavor of my childhood.
# 这边正在修路 车也进不来
The road is under construction so we can't drive.
# 吃个烧鸡好难啊
It's so tiring.
# 快到了
Almost there.
# 你好 还有烧鸡吗
Hello, is there any braised chicken?
# 有 带走吗 对的
Yes. Takeout? Yes.
# 要几个
How many?
# 多少钱了
How much is it?
# 22一斤
22￥ for 1 Jin (500g).
# 要一个就行
I just want one.
# 要一般大的就行吧
A normal sized one?
# 对
Yeah.
# 因为疫情 烧鸡做的没有以前那么多了
Because of the pandemic, the restaurant has reduced the amount of braised chicken for sale.
# 但每天还是能够吃到刚出锅的
But each day there are still just-out-of-the-wok braised chicken for customers.
# 烧鸡的做法呢 大体都是
The recipe is normally,
# 先炖 再上色 最后捞出来浸泡到老汤里
first braise, then coloring and finally immersing in broth.
# 但是不同的店 用的大料不同
However, different restaurants have different seasoning.
# 口味上 还是有一些差别的
So the falvors are different.
# 扣大盖了
Put on lid.
# 盖上盖子 鸡要足足炖半个多小时
After putting on lid, chicken must be braised for over half an hour,
# 才能让肉炖透 料入味
to soften the meat and let the flavor penetrate the chicken.
# 刚捞出来的鸡 颜色只是微微的酱油的颜色
Chicken has only faint color from soy sauce when taken out.
# 如果说 想要换得真身
If, say, we want real authentic braised chicken.
# 还得把锅底烧红 用白糖熏烤上色
We need to hot the wok and roast the chicken with white sugar.
# 看到没 买到了烧鸡
Look. I bought braised chicken.
# 这一只烧鸡是两斤多重
This one weighs more than 2 Jin (1kg).
# 因为它是22块钱一斤
Since the price is 22￥ for 1 Jin (500g),
# 咱们这一只是46块钱的
this one worth 46￥.
# 走吧 回家吃烧鸡了
Let's go home and eat braised chicken.
# 烧鸡还是热的
The chicken is still hot.
# 隔着袋子 你都能闻到香味
You can smell the aroma outside the plastic bag.
# 我们要赶快回家
We need to hurry back home.
# 享受这顿美味
And enjoy this delicious food.
# 撕烧鸡 应该不是什么技术活吧
Tearing the chicken is no technical stuff right?
# 可大可小
No regular sizes.
# 看撕烧鸡的人的心情是怎么样的
What is it like to look at me tearing this chicken?
# 大部分的情况下
Under most circumstances,
# 撕烧鸡的人是有权力
the person who tears the chicken has the right
# 把烧鸡
to put some
# 塞进自己的嘴里的
inside her mouth.
# 好香啊
It smells so good.
# 烧鸡的皮特别薄 像褶皱一样
The skin is thin as wrinkles.
# 它是相比于鸡肉来说 更咸 更入味的
It's more salted than the meat and has better flavor.
# 反观鸡肉呢 就是更白嫩一些
On the other hand, the meat is tenderer and whiter.
# 我要继续啃鸡腿了 拜拜
I'll keep biting on my chicken legs then. Byebye.